A Guide to the Papers of Benjamin A. Banks 1900-1974
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Benjamin A. Banks 1900-1974
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 6
18 Hollinger Document Cases and 1 Drop-front Print Box; 8 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions. Questions on literary property rights should be directed to the Special Collections coordinator.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Helen G. Banks, May 18, 1976
Accession Number: A76-15
Biographical/Historical Information
Benjamin A. Banks (original family name Bonk) was born, according to his own testimony, on May 18, 1884, in Baltimore, Maryland. Soon after his father's death his family moved to Norfolk, Virginia, where they had relatives living. Banks received his only formal education in Norfolk's public schools. He then studied law on his own and was admitted to the Virginia Bar in November 1909. He continued to practice law until his death on April 27, 1974.
From 1908 through 1913, Banks served as editor and publisher of The Galaxy, a literary magazine which he hoped would enjoy critical and financial success not only in Norfolk but throughout the South. His colleague in this unsuccessful effort was local poet George Viett, who remained Banks' close friend until his death in 1943. Banks' first forays into the political arena in Norfolk were quite successful. He served on the Norfolk Board of Alderman from 1908 to 1911 at which point he resigned to take up the seat he had recently won in the Virginia House of Delegates. Banks did not run for reelection however, and all his subsequent attempts to return to public office: Virginia State Senate (1923); Commonwealth's Attorney for Norfolk (1925); House of Delegates (1933, 1937) ended in defeat. Nonetheless, he played an active role in Norfolk's Democratic politics from the 1900's through the 1940's. He participated in most local election campaigns and was frequently called on to make radio speeches on behalf of the candidates. For example, he successfully supported Norman Hamilton against Colgate Darden for Congress in 1936 and then aided Darden to defeat Hamilton in 1938. Banks was elected Norfolk chairman of the Virginia Liberal League in 1918 and, in 1937, he helped found the Citizen's Democratic League, a group that supported candidates against the dominant local Democratic organization, with only limited success, until its demise in the early 1940's. Banks was also an active campaigner for Democratic presidential candidates from Woodrow Wilson to George McGovern. He was particularly active in the Roosevelt clubs that developed in the 1930's.
Banks was a prominent member of the Norfolk Jewish community and was especially interested in promoting better understanding among Christians and Jews. He worked toward this goal in many letters written to local newspapers, especially in his annual Christmas "epistles." His numerous letters to the editors of the leading Norfolk and Richmond newspapers dealt with many topics, more often with political issues - local, state, and national. Their range-from Prohibition and the Ku Klux Klan to Vietnam and Watergate - symbolize the length of his concerns with political issues. Bank's letters also won him plaudits from many members of the Tidewater community and from political figures throughout the entire Commonwealth of Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Benjamin A. Banks span the years of 1900-1974. Personal papers include letters to the editor, speeches, and literary materials. Political papers span Banks' political career (1908-1913) and his continuing involvement in political issues through the 1940's. Also included in the collection are scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, photographs, memorabilia, and Manuals of the Senate and House of Delegates of Virginia for the years 1908, 1912, 1926, 1934.
Arrangement
Organization
The collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Personal Papers. Includes personal correspondence; "Letters to the Editor" (1910-1972); miscellaneous material re. Judaism, Christianity, and their relationship; speeches and material for speeches; Literary materials for and copies of The Galaxy; papers relating to George Viett, Norfolk poet-author. Oversized memorabilia are stored in the dropfront box.
Series II: Political Papers. Includes material regarding Banks' own short political career (1908-1913), his involvement in Norfolk politics from the 1900's through the 1940's, and his participation in presidential campaigns in Virginia (especially in Norfolk) throughout this same period. Also contains correspondence relating to his largely unsuccessful efforts to obtain patronage jobs from both the Wilson and Roosevelt Administrations.
Series III: Scrapbooks. Contain newspaper clippings and some correspondence regarding his political activities; clippings of letters to the editors; some items relating to Judaism.
Series IV: Pictorial Records. Includes a small number of miscellaneous photographs; oversized photographs are kept in the drop-front box. A large framed photograph of the "Bench and Bar of Norfolk, Va. 1922" is stored separately.
Series V: Books. Three Books from Banks' personal library; Manuals of the Senate and House of Delegates of Virginia for the years 1908, 1912, 1926, 1934.
Series VI: Memorabilia. Includes Law License, Certificates, Photographs.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically within series.
Contents List
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Sub Series A: Correspondence
    - General 1910-1973 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Polan Banks 1943-1974 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annie 1914 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Caroline 1912 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ernestine 1921 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hortense 1919 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hortense 1919-1921 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence re: Education League Scholarship 1906 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sub Series B: Letters to the Editor
    - Letters re. Press (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Editors of Virginian-Pilot 1924-1972 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with Editors of Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch, Richmond Times-Dispatch 1944-1971 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Virginian-Pilot 1924-1963 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Virginian-Pilot 1964-1972 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch 1916-1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch 1960-1972 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Richmond News-Leader; Richmond Times-Dispatch 1942-1973 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 1940-1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Unknown Papers 1907-1956 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Tributes to Others 1943-1973 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Fan Letters": General 1948-1973 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Fan Letters": Irving Kline 1958-1974 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Fan Letters": Miscellaneous Political Figures 1940-1974 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Fan Letters": Colgate Darden; Floyd Kellam; Richard Kellam; Sydney Kellam 1953-1973 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Clippings 1920-1929 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Clippings 1930-1939 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clippings 1940-1949 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Clippings 1950-1959 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Clippings 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Clippings 1970-1974 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clippings Dates Unknown (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Material re: Press Handling of Letters to the Editor (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings re: Banks (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sub Series C: Knights of Pythias
    - Banks' Speeches before Group 1940-1970 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Material re: Banks' Involvement, 1944-1946, 1948 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Material re: Lodge #10 (Norfolk) 1943-1967 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Material re: National Organization (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sub Series D: Sons of Italy
    - Correspondence; Misc. material re. relationship with Banks 1912-1972 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sub Series E: Legal Practice
    - Documents; Newspaper Clippings 1920-1974 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Items (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sub Series F: Literary Material: The Galaxy
    - Index to Scrapbooks; The Galaxy; Letters (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Material re: The Galaxy 1907-1913 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The Galaxy: Woodrow Wilson Inauguration Issue, March, 1913. Bound Volumes The Galaxy: Vols. I &II, September 1907-August 1909; Vols. III &IV, September 1909 - October 1913 1907-1913 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Aphorisms; Quotations (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Clippings; Articles; Poems (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sub Series G: Speeches
    - Speeches on Miscellaneous Topics (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Material for Speeches (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Speeches Given by others (perhaps Written by Banks) (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Speeches to others; Speeches; Written pieces (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sub Series H: George Viett Material
    - Published Works; Memorabilia 1910-1930 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Unpublished Writings 1900-1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters to the Editor 1903-1941 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1918-1941 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Clippings of letters to the Editor 1910-1919 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Clippings of Letters to the Editor 1920-1929 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Clippings of Letters to the Editor 1930-1939 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Clippings of letters to the Editor 1940-1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Clippings of letters to the Editor Dates Unknown (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Letters, Columns Written under Gifo G. Everett Pen Name 1920-1929 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence re: Viett-Banks Dispute May 1919 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Viett's Death 1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Misc. Items about Viett 1900-1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Disposition of Viett's Personal Papers 1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Sub Series J: Religion; Christianity
    - General Material on Religion (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General: Versions of speech on "Law and Religion" (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General: Liberty, A Magazine of Religious Freedom, (Misc. Copies) 1946, 1963 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Misc. Material (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Misc. Articles 1820-1966 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Misc. Newspaper clippings 1900-1970 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Publications of the American Board of Missions to the Jews 1950-1960 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Christmas Letters to Editors (Largely to Norfolk Press) 1947-1968 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Misc. Correspondence (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sub Series K: Judaism
    - Misc. Speeches and Written Pieces (Banks) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Material (Banks) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Letters to the Editor (Largely Norfolk Press) 1915-1972 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Jefferson Society of Norfolk (Jewish Discussion Group) 1906-1911 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Norfolk Jewish Community: Misc. Material 1948-1955 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with American Jewish Archives 1970-1973 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
    - List of Items Sent to American Jewish Archives 1970 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Rabbi Harold D. Hahn 1964-1973 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with Rabbi Alan Steinbach; Misc. material re: Steinbach 1923-1972 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Misc. Correspondence 1948-1972 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Misc. Articles 1889-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Newspaper Clippings 1900-1967 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Misc. Publications re: Judaism 1946-1960 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
    - American Judaism 1957-1965 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Misc. Writings on Zionism (Banks) 1915-1969 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Misc. Newspaper clippings re: Zionism 1915-1970 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Misc. Non-Jewish Publications re: Zionism 1948, 1969 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
    - The New Palestine; Congress Weekly 1948-1950 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
    - B'nai B'rith Publications 1910-1913, 1960 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Misc. B'nai B'rith Material (Banks) (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
- Series II: Political Papers
  - Sub Series A: Norfolk Politics
    - Self-Summary of Banks' Political Career 1910-1960 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Service on Norfolk Board of Aldermen 1908-1911 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Norfolk, Virginia": Booklet Prepared by Banks for Industrial Commission 1909 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Controversy over Banks' Origins: General 1911-1912 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Controversy over Banks' Origins: Dispute within B'nai B'rith Lodge 1912-1913 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Sub Series B: Virginia House of Delegates Career
    - Misc. Material 1911-1913 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Speeches in House 1912 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Bills Introduced 1912 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Campaign for State Senate 1923 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Campaign for Commonwealth's Attorney 1925 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Campaign for House of Delegates 1933 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Hamilton-Darden Congressional Campaign 1936 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Sub Series C: Citizens' Democratic League
    - Misc. Material re: Goals of Group 1937-1940 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Misc. Campaign Material 1937-1940 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1937 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Hamilton-Darden Congressional Campaign: Banks' Speeches 1938 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Hamilton-Darden campaign: Campaign Materials 1938 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Sub Series D: Norfolk Politics
    - 1940 City Council Election 1940 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Special Election, 2nd Congressional District 1941 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Citizens' Democratic League: Misc. Material 1940-1949 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Misc. Material 1960-1969 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
    - E. Vincent Wyatt Campaign for City Treasurer 1965-1966 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Misc. Banks' Speeches (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Sub Series E: State Politics
    - A. Willis Robertson's U. S. Senate Campaign 1966 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Henry Howell's Gubernatorial Campaign 1969 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Misc. Banks' Speeches re: Statewide Elections 1910-1950 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Sub Series F: Presidential Campaigns
    - Wilson Campaign and Administration 1912-1918 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Al Smith Campaign: Banks' Speech 1928 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Roosevelt Campaigns: Correspondence 1932-1944 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Roosevelt Campaigns: Misc. Material, 1932-1936 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Roosevelt Campaigns: Bank's Speeches 1932-1944 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Roosevelt Administrations: Misc. Material 1933-1939 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 15)
    - 1952 Campaign: Misc. Material (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 16)
    - 1960 Campaign: Misc. Material (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 17)
    - 1968 Campaign: Letters to the Editor Sept.-Oct., 1968 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Sub Series G: Political Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous 1907-1971 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Norman Hamilton 1934-1936 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Norman Hamilton (After election to Congress) 1936-1937 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Colgate Darden: General 1935-1969 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with Wilson Administration re: Government Job 1912-1918 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Virginia Politicians re: Support for Job in Wilson Administration 1913-1920 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with Simon Wolf re: Efforts to Obtain Government job 1914 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Applications for Collectorship of Port of Norfolk 1914 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence with Dept. of Justice re: Government Job, 1933-1934 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Dept. of Justice re: Job Obtained in War Risk Insurance Office, 1934-1936 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Misc. Correspondence re: Dept. of Justice Jobs 1933-1934, 1936 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with Harry Byrd, Sr. re: Dept. of Justice Job (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with Colgate Darden re: Dept. of Justice Job 1933-1934 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with Bernard Baruch re: Dept. of Justice Job 1934 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence with Treasury Dept. re: Government Job 1934-1939 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Correpondence re: Government Jobs (Largely with Colgate Darden) 1939-1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with Congressmen Winder Harris re: Government Job 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Material re: "Negro Problem" - Including Supreme Court's Role 1903-1958 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 4)
    - "Legal Articles: (Considerable Material re: Supreme Court) 1920-1970 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 5)
    - The Growler: Norfolk Political Weekly 1905 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 6)
    - The Free-Lance: Norfolk Political Weekly 1905 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 7)
    - The Free-Lance 1906 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 8)
- Series III: Scrapbooks
  - Index to Scrapbooks (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Book #1: pp. 1-36 (Largely Political) 1906-1912 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Book #1: pp. 37-71 (Largely Political) 1906-1912 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Book #3: pp. 1-38 (Largely Political) 1924-1958 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Book #3: pp. 38-78 (Largely Political) 1924-1958 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Book #4: pp. 38-78 (Largely Political) 1912-1924 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Bound Volume Letters to Editors; Misc. Newspaper clippings 1906-1972 (Box-folder Box 15)
  - "Political and Campaign Scrapbook" (Presidential Campaigns 1912, 1932-1934 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Scrapbook: Jewish Topics; Items from The Galaxy 1906-1913 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Pictorial Records
  - B.A. Banks in Law Office, ca. 1920 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Bank's State Senate Campaign 1923 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Photographs (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Photograph of Norfolk Industrial Commission, ca. 1909 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Photograph of 7th Annual Harbors and Rivers Congress, Washington, D.C, December 18, 1910 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Group Portrait of 1912 Virginia House of Delegates (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Large framed photograph of the Norfolk Bar Association (1922) is stored separately
- Series V: Books
  - Flanders, Henry. The Lives and Times of the Chief Justices of the Supreme Court of the United States. Vol. I: John Jay-John Rutledge. Philadelphia: Lippincott, Grambo &Co., 1855 (Box-folder Box 18)
  - Harris, Joel Chandler. Life of Henry W. Grady. New York: Casssell 1890 (Box-folder Box 18)
  - U. S. House of Representatives. Henry D. Flood. Memorial Addresses Delivered in Congress. Washington, D.C.: Gov't. Printing Office 1922 (Box-folder Box 18)
  - Manual of the Senate and House of Delegates, Virginia. 1908, 1912, 1926, 1934 (Box-folder Box 18)
- Series VI: Memorabilia
  - License to Practice Law in Virginia November 12, 1909 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Certificate of Election to the House of Delegates November 27, 1911 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Commendation from Italian Societies of Norfolk 1912 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))
  - Authorization to Plead Cases before the U.S. Supreme Court January 21, 1929 (Box-folder Box 19 (Drop-front Print Box))